<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="GuideIntroduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>Geeqie is an image viewer that makes navigation of images easy. Images can be viewed as thumbnails, in multiple windows or in full screen mode.</para>
  <para>Geeqie is an image manager, with complete copy, move, rename, and delete functions available at the press of a button.</para>
  <para>Extensive image collections can be easily handled using a combination of Geeqie's flexible Keyword facility and powerful Image searches.</para>
  <para>Image collections can be refined with a duplicate image finder.</para>
  <para>Geeqie is ideal for making presentations. A slide-show feature is built in, and Geeqie can be remotely controlled either via command line scripts or an infra-red device. Information such as f-stop, shutter speed and descriptive text can be overlayed onto the image display.</para>
  <para>There is no need to import images into Geeqie - simply point Geeqie to a folder containing images, and your data will be displayed.</para>
  <para>Geeqie is an image viewer, not an image editor. However, Geeqie can be configured to call external image editors such as the Gimp, resulting in a very powerful combination.</para>
  <para />
  <section id="Features">
    <title>Features</title>
    <section id="BasicFeatures">
      <title>Basic Features</title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="Iconview" endterm="titleIconview" />
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideImagePresentationFullscreen" endterm="titleGuideImagePresentationFullscreen" />
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideImagePresentationSlideshow" endterm="titleGuideImagePresentationSlideshow" />
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideImageManagement" endterm="titleGuideImageManagement" />
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideCollections" endterm="titleGuideCollections" />
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para />
    </section>
    <section id="AdvancedFeatures">
      <title>Advanced Features</title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideImageSearch" endterm="titleGuideImageSearch" />
          <para>Image Search based on many parameters</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideImageSearchFindingDuplicates" endterm="titleGuideImageSearchFindingDuplicates" />
          <para>Find image duplicates based on image content</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideSidebarsInfo" endterm="titleExif" />
          <para>View IPTC, and view and edit Exif and XMP data stored in images</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideSidebarsSortManager" endterm="titleGuideSidebarsSortManager" />
          <para>Simple Sort Manager to quickly sort a folder of images into other folders</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideImageManagementRename" endterm="titleGuideImageManagementRename" />
          <para>Rename images in bulk</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="InformationandhistogramOverlay" endterm="titleInformationandhistogramOverlay" />
          <para>Overlay the image with a panel showing user-definable data</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="Keywords" endterm="titleKeywords" />
          <para>Add XMP keywords to images, and recall those images with the search function</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <link linkend="GuideOptions" endterm="titleGuideOptions" />
          <para>Geeqie is a very configurable application</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>“An application that displays images.” - This was, and still is, the primary goal of Geeqie. Over time image management features have been added, but the core purpose of Geeqie remains the same.</para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
