<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="GuideFaq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
  <para />
  <section id="Imageviewing">
    <title>Image viewing</title>
    <para />
    <section id="HowdoIkeepimagessmallerthanthevisibleareafromenlargingwhenthezoomissettofittowindow">
      <title>How do I keep images smaller than the visible area from enlarging when the zoom is set to “fit to window” ?</title>
      <para>
        In the
        <link linkend="GuideOptionsImage">Preferences Image dialog</link>
        , disable “Allow enlargement of image for zoom to fit”.
      </para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Commandline">
    <title>Command line</title>
    <para />
    <section id="HowdoIopenanimageinanexistingGeeqieapplication">
      <title>How do I open an image in an existing Geeqie application ?</title>
      <para>Use the “--remote” command line option to send commands to an existing Geeqie, for a list of commands supported by the remote switch run:</para>
      <programlisting>geeqie --remote-help</programlisting>
      <para />
    </section>
    <section id="HowdoIsettheslideshowdelaywhenstartingGeeqieinslideshowfromthecommandline">
      <title>How do I set the slide show delay when starting Geeqie in slide show from the command line ?</title>
      <para>The delay can not be set when used with the standard --slideshow command line switch, as --slideshow uses the delay stored in the configuration file.</para>
      <para>For this, use the remote command --slideshow-start to start the slide show after setting the delay with --delay=. The order of the command line is important. For example for a 12 second slide show delay use:</para>
      <programlisting>geeqie --remote  --delay=12 --slideshow-start</programlisting>
      <para>Note that if geeqie is running prior to this command, the slide show should also be stopped prior to changing the delay:</para>
      <programlisting>geeqie --remote --slideshow-stop --delay=12 --slideshow-start</programlisting>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Miscellaneous">
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>
    <para />
    <section id="IwanttobeabletoeditimageswithGeeqie">
      <title>I want to be able to edit images with Geeqie</title>
      <para>
        Geeqie is an image
        <emphasis role="i">viewer</emphasis>
        . There is, and never will be, a plan to add editing features. I recommend gimp for image editing.
      </para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="ExifRotation">
    <title>Exif Auto Rotation</title>
    <para />
    <section id="HowdotheExifauto-rotationcommandswork">
      <title>How do the Exif auto-rotation commands work?</title>
      <para>
        Image auto-rotation works in either of two modes, set by
        <link linkend="MetadataMiscellaneous">Write altered image orientation to the metadata</link>
        option.
      </para>
      <para>
        <guilabel>Write altered image orientation to the metadata not set</guilabel>
        <para />
        If you change the orientation of an image using any of the available commands, the image will always be displayed in the modified orientation. This new orientation is stored in temporary data structures associated with each image file. When Geeqie closes, these changes will be lost.
      </para>
      <warning>
        <para>It is not possible to determine if the image as displayed is the original image or one which has been temporarily rotated.</para>
      </warning>
      <para>
        If the option
        <link linkend="Editmenu">Auto rotate image using EXIF information</link>
        is selected, any images which have Exif orientation data will also be shown rotated. However, any rotation you have selected manually will always over-ride the embedded Exif rotation value.
      </para>
      <para>
        <guilabel>Write altered image orientation to the metadata set</guilabel>
        <para />
        <para>If you change the orientation of an image using any of the available commands, this new orientation is stored in a metadata write queue.</para>
        <para>
          If the option
          <link linkend="Editmenu">Auto rotate image using EXIF information</link>
          is selected, any images which have Exif orientation data will be shown rotated, including any in the metadata write queue.
        </para>
        <para>
          However if the option
          <link linkend="Editmenu">Auto rotate image using EXIF information</link>
          is not selected, no images will be auto-rotated. If you have manually rotated any images, the metadata write icon on the status bar will alert you to that fact. Clicking the icon will give a list of the modified files.
        </para>
      </para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
