<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideImageMarks">
  <title id="titleGuideImageMarks">Marking Images</title>
  <para>Marks are intended as a temporary method of grouping and filtering sets of images.</para>
  <para>
    <link linkend="Keywords" endterm="titleKeywords" />
    are intended as a permanent method of identifying sets of images, and to this end it is possible to link any mark with any keyword.
  </para>
  <para>
    The
    <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
    menu gives access to the marks operations of setting, filtering and intersection.
  </para>
  <para>There are 10 individual marks, any of which can be associated with an image simply by pressing the 0 to 9 keys on the keyboard, where key 0 represents mark 10.</para>
  <para>
    If the
    <guimenu>Show Marks</guimenu>
    menu has been selected, each image will have a set of 10 check-boxes displayed adjacent to it in the file pane in both icon and list mode. In addition a set of 10 check-boxes will be shown at the top of the files pane. Clicking any of these will filter the displayed list.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the
    <link linkend="InformationandhistogramOverlay" endterm="titleInformationandhistogramOverlay" />
    is being displayed, the currently set marks for the image are shown. It is not necessary to include an entry into the overlay template for this to happen.
  </para>
  <para>
    A keyword can be associated with a single mark by right-clicking on the keyword in the sidebar panel. When a meta-data write operation for a file is triggered either
    <link linkend="Buttons">manually</link>
    or as defined in
    <link linkend="GuideOptionsMetadata" endterm="titleGuideOptionsMetadata" />
    , the keyword data indicated by the current set of mark-to-keyword links will be written.
  </para>
  <para>
    The associations between keywords and marks is preserved when Geeqie is shut down. The current setting of marks can also be optionally saved - the setting is in the
    <link linkend="Behaviour">Behavior tab of Preferences</link>
    .
  </para>
  <para />
  <para />
</section>
