<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideOptionsBehavior">
  <title>Behavior Options</title>
  <para>This section describes the options presented under the Behavior Tab of the preferences dialog.</para>
  <section id="Delete">
    <title>Delete</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Confirm file delete</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prompts for confirmation before deleting files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>
            Enable
            <keycap>Delete key</keycap>
          </guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Disable this to disassociate the delete file function from the
            <keycap>Delete</keycap>
            key.
          </para>
          <para>
            If
            <emphasis>Confirm file delete</emphasis>
            , above, is disabled, accidentally hitting the
            <keycap>Delete</keycap>
            can result in files being erroneously deleted without warning. Disabling the
            <keycap>Delete</keycap>
            key will prevent this. The
            <code>
              Ctrl +
              <keycap>D</keycap>
            </code>
            key sequence is not affected.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Safe Delete</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Moves deleted files to a temporary folder, for easy retrieval of deleted files. Files in the temporary folder are retained until the maximum size is reached, at which point deleting additional files will result in the removal of the oldest files to reclaim the space needed for the new files.</para>
          <note>
            <para>
              Files moved to the Safe Delete folder are prefixed with a six digit number in the format:
              <literal>nnnnnn_FILENAME</literal>
              <para />
              This is used by the delete feature to distinguish which files to remove first when clearing space for new files.
              <para />
              The digit counter increments with each deleted file.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Folder</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The location of the folder used by the Safe Delete feature.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Maximum size</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The size to use for the Safe Delete folder, in megabytes. Note that setting this value to 0 (zero) will disable any limit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Clear button</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Removes all files contained in the Safe Delete folder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>View button</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Changes the Geeqie main window to display the contents of the Safe Delete folder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section id="Behaviour">
    <title>Behavior</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Descend folders in tree view</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This will allow Geeqie to read sub folder content to determine if it should display expander indicators in the folder tree view.</para>
          <note>
            <para>Disable this if Geeqie wakes up auto mounted network shares, or takes too long to initially display the folder view.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>In place renaming</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When renaming a single file, this will allow the rename entry to appear directly over the original filename.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>List directory view uses single click to enter</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If selected, a single click will enter a directory, rather than the GTK+ default of a double click.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Recent folder list maximum size</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the number of entries to be saved from the recent open folder list drop-down box. The number of entries displayed in the current session is unlimited.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Drag'n drop icon size</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the width and height of the icon generated from image and displayed when doing drag and drop actions. High resolution screens may require to increase this number.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section id="Navigation">
    <title>Navigation</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Progressive keyboard scrolling</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This will cause image panning speed to gradually accelerate when holding down the keyboard arrows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Keyboard scrolling step multiplier:</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Defines the amount to pan an image when using the keyboard arrows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Mouse wheel scrolls image</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The default is for the mouse wheel to change the image, and to scroll the image when
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            is used in combination with the wheel. Enabling this swaps the behavior so that operating the wheel will scroll the image, and holding down
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            will change the image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Navigation by left or middle click on image</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If selected, mouse left-click will select the next image; mouse middle-click will select the previous image.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Play video by left click on image</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If selected, mouse left-click on an image belonging to the video class will start a program chosen in a box below.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section id="Debugging">
    <title>Debugging</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Debug level</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Displayed when compiled with the option --enable-debug-log. This defines the verbosity of debug info sent to console and log window (0 disables the debug output).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Log Window max. lines</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The maximum number of data lines to be displayed. The window will show the most recent data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</section>
