<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideMainWindowFolderPane">
  <title id="titleGuideMainWindowFolderPane">Folder pane</title>
  <para>The folder pane contains the menu bar, tool bar, path entry, and folder list.</para>
  <para />
  <section id="Menubar">
    <title>Menu bar</title>
    <para>
      The main menu of the window. The functions available from the main menu are described in the
      <link linkend="GuideMainWindowMenus">Menus</link>
      chapter.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Toolbar">
    <title>Tool bar</title>
    <para>
      The tool bar includes buttons for often used operations. The tool bar can be hidden or shown by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Hide toolbar</emphasis>
      from the
      <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis>
      menu.
    </para>
    <table frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="3" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
        <thead rowsep="1" colsep="1">
          <row>
            <entry>Icon</entry>
            <entry>Tooltip</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="icon_thumb.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Show thumbnails</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>This button is active when the file list is in list view mode, and activating it will toggle the display of thumbnails.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="go-previous.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Back</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Move back in folder history</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="go-up.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Up</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Move up one folder</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="user-home.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Home</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Change the main window to display the contents of the user's home folder</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="view-refresh.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Refresh folder display</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Refresh the contents of the file pane</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="zoom-in.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Zoom in</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Increase the image display size.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="zoom-out.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Zoom out</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Decrease the image display size.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="zoom-fit-best.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Zoom to fit</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>This will size the image to fit within the window</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="zoom-original.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Zoom 1:1</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Restore zoom to the image's original size.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="preferences-desktop.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Preferences</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                Displays the
                <link linkend="GuideOptions">Preferences window</link>
                .
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="icon_float.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Float file list</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Toggle the folder pane, file pane, and status bar between the main window and a secondary window.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Pathentry">
    <title>Path entry</title>
    <para>This displays the active folder of the window and allows typing a location.</para>
    <para>
      A folder or file can be typed into the entry to quickly change to a desired location or image, the main window will update after pressing the
      <code>Enter</code>
      key. Tab completion is also available in the path entry.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Tab completion uses the
        <keycode>Tab</keycode>
        key, press the
        <keycode>Down</keycode>
        key to move the focus from the entry.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>Next to the path entry is a button with a down arrow, clicking this will display a drop down list containing the most recent locations viewed. The list is ordered such that the most recent location is at the top. Selecting a location from the drop down list will change the window to display the location.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Folderlist">
    <title>Folder list</title>
    <para>This pane consists of two sections: a folder pane and a shortcuts pane. The shortcuts pane may be hidden or revealed simply by moving the vertical divider to or from the extreme left.</para>
    <section id="folders">
      <title>Folders</title>
      <para>This displays a list of sub folders contained in the active folder, or a tree that includes all folders in the file system.</para>
      <para>
        A
        <emphasis role="strong">context menu</emphasis>
        can be displayed by clicking the right mouse button on the folder pane or pressing the menu key while the folder pane has the focus
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="Shortcutslist">
      <title>Shortcuts</title>
      <para>This is a list of shortcuts (bookmarks) to commonly used folders or images. A context menu will appear by right clicking on an item, or pressing the menu key when the item has the focus.</para>
      <para>Folders or images can be added to the list by activating the Add button at the bottom of the pane, or dragging a folder or image onto the list.</para>
      <para>
        To edit an item select
        <emphasis role="bold">Properties</emphasis>
        from its context menu. A dialog will appear allowing the Name, Path, and Icon for the item to be changed. Select OK to close the dialog and apply the changes, or Cancel to close the dialog and discard the changes.
      </para>
      <para>
        To change the order of the list, select
        <emphasis role="bold">Move up</emphasis>
        or
        <emphasis role="bold">Move down</emphasis>
        from the item's context menu. To move an item with the keyboard move the focus to that item, then press
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          <keycap>Up</keycap>
        </keycombo>
        or
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          <keycap>Down</keycap>
        </keycombo>
        to move the item.
      </para>
      <para>
        To remove an item from the list select
        <emphasis role="bold">Remove</emphasis>
        from it's context menu.
      </para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Listview">
    <title>List view</title>
    <para>
      This mode can be enabled by from the
      <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis>
      menu, from the context menu, or pressing
      <code>Ctrl + T</code>
      .
    </para>
    <para>The list view mode displays sub folders contained in the active folder in a standard vertical list. The parent folder can be selected with the folder named “..”.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Treeview">
    <title>Tree view</title>
    <para>
      This mode can be enabled by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Tree</emphasis>
      from the View menu, pressing
      <code>Ctrl + T</code>
      , or selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">View as tree</emphasis>
      from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      The tree view mode displays all folders in the file system, starting with the root folder and branching out to include sub folders. A folder branch can be expanded or collapsed by clicking the expander next to each folder icon, or by pressing the respective
      <code>+</code>
      or
      <code>-</code>
      keys when the folder branch has the focus.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Sorting">
    <title>Sorting</title>
    <para>The order of the folder names will match the order selected for the file pane. Sort order can be changed by clicking the sort area of the status bar or from the context menu of the file pane.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Contextmenu">
    <title>Context menu</title>
    <para>
      Right clicking the mouse or pressing the menu key while the folder pane has focus will display a menu. The menu functions will perform the same as those that match the window's
      <link linkend="GuideMainWindowMenus">menu bar</link>
      , however a few functions are unique to the context menu:
    </para>
    <table frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="3" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
        <thead rowsep="1" colsep="1">
          <row>
            <entry>Icon</entry>
            <entry>Text</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="go-up.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Up to parent</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>This will change the window to display the contents of the parent folder.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>Slide show</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                Start a
                <link linkend="GuideImagePresentationSlideshow">slide show</link>
                that contains all images in the selected folder.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>Slide show recursive</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                Start a
                <link linkend="GuideImagePresentationSlideshow">slide show</link>
                that contains all images in the selected folder, and all images in the sub folders of that folder.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="edit-find.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Find duplicates</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This will open a new
                <link linkend="GuideImageSearchFindingDuplicates">find duplicates</link>
                window containing all images in the selected folder.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="edit-find.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Find duplicates recursive</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This will open a new
                <link linkend="GuideImageSearchFindingDuplicates">find duplicates</link>
                window containing all image in the selected folder, and all images in the sub folders of that folder.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>New folder</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Creates a new folder that is a sub folder of the selected folder.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>Rename</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Renames the selected folder.</para>
              <warning>
                <emphasis role="bold">Warning:</emphasis>
                Renaming a folder will not update metadata, such as keywords, or cached thumbnails for images contained in that folder, the data will be lost.
              </warning>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="edit-delete.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Delete</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Delete file or folder</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>Copy path</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Copy sjkhsdlfjhvfljhDelete file or folder</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>View as list</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Switches to list tree mode of the folder pane.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>View as tree</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Switches to tree mode of the folder pane.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>Show hiden files</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Switches to list tree mode of the folder pane.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic fileref="view-refresh.png" />
              </guiicon>
            </entry>
            <entry>Refresh</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Switches to tree mode of the folder pane.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Draganddrop">
    <title>Drag and drop</title>
    <para>Image files can be dropped onto folders displayed in the folder pane. A menu will appear allowing you to select to move or copy the dropped images into the target folder. The list will automatically scroll up or down when the drag pointer is near the respective top or bottom of the list. When in tree mode, hovering over a folder for a brief period of time will expand that folder.</para>
    <para>The folders can used as a drag source for drag and drop, for example to add images in a folder to a collection window. However drag and drop can not be used to move or copy folders in Geeqie.</para>
    <para>
      Using
      <code>Shift</code>
      key while dragging is a shortcut to move action. Menu will not appear but move will occur.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using
      <code>Ctrl</code>
      key while dragging is a shortcut to copy action. Menu will not appear but copy will occur.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
</section>
