<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideMainWindowFilePane">
  <title id="titleGuideMainWindowFilePane">File Pane</title>
  <para>The file pane displays the images contained in the active folder. It has two modes of display, allows multiple selection, and can initiate drag and drop operations.</para>
  <para>
    A
    <emphasis role="strong">context menu</emphasis>
    can be displayed by clicking the right mouse button on the file pane or pressing the menu key while the file pane has the focus.
  </para>
  <para />
  <section id="Listview">
    <title>List view</title>
    <para>
      This mode can be enabled by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">List</emphasis>
      from the
      <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis>
      menu, pressing <code>Ctrl + L</code>, or unselecting
      <emphasis role="bold">View as icons</emphasis>
      from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>The list view mode displays images in a standard vertical list. Three columns provide the file name, size in bytes, and the time the contents were last modified.</para>
    <para>
      Thumbnails can be displayed next to each file in the list, to toggle thumbnails on or off by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Thumbnails</emphasis>
      from the
      <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis>
      menu, pressing <code>T</code>, clicking <imagedata fileref="icon_thumb.png"></imagedata> on the tool bar, or selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Show thumbnails</emphasis>
      from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      <link linkend="GuideOptionsFiltering">Grouped sidecar files</link>
      are represented by the main file with an expander. Clicking on the expander shows sidecar files.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Iconview">
    <title id="titleIconview">Icon view</title>
    <para>
      This mode can be enabled by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Icons</emphasis>
      from the View menu, pressing <code>Ctrl + I</code>, or selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">View as icons</emphasis>
      from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>The icon view mode displays images as thumbnails in a grid, and by default a file name below each thumbnail.</para>
    <para>
      The 
      file name displayed below each thumbnail can be turned on or off by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Show filename text</emphasis>
      from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      <link linkend="GuideOptionsFiltering">Grouped sidecar files</link>
      are represented by the main file. For accessing sidecars switch to List mode.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Filefilter">
    <title id="titleFilefilter">File Filter</title>
    <para>
      A filter box can be opened by selecting
      <emphasis role="bold">Show File Filter</emphasis>
      from the View menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      Characters you type into this box will be used for pattern matching to select the files displayed.
      <link linkend="GuideReferencePCRE">Regular expressions</link>
      are used in this field.
      <para />
      For basic pattern matching "JPG" will match any filename containing those characters.
      <para />
      If you type a newline, the text will be saved in the dropdown box list. The last 10 items are saved.
      <para />
      To delete an item, select it from the drop-down list, click on the text box to select the text, and then press
      <keycap>Delete</keycap>
      followed by
      <keycap>Enter</keycap>
      .
    </para>
    <para>By default filtering is case-insensitive. A checkbox labelled "Case" permits the filter to be made case-sensitive.
    </para>
    <para>Additionally a drop-down box permits any of the file <link linkend="Filetypes">Classes</link> to be selected or deselected from the viewed list.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Multipleselection">
    <title>Multiple selection</title>
    <para>It is possible to select more than one image from the file pane. Multiple files can be selected with several methods:</para>
    <para />
    <section id="Mouse">
      <title>Mouse</title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Ctrl</code> + Primary mouse button will add or remove the file from the selection.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Middle mouse button will toggle selection of the file.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Shift</code> + Primary mouse button will select all images between the clicked and focused image, or it will unselect all those images if the clicked image is already selected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Shift + Ctrl</code> + Primary mouse button works as Shift + Primary mouse button, but will not change the selection of files outside the region between the focus and clicked image.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para />
    </section>
    <section id="Keyboard">
      <title>Keyboard</title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Ctrl + Arrows</code> will move the focus without changing the selection.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Ctrl + Space</code> will toggle selection of the focused image.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Shift + Arrows</code> will select a region of images.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Shift + Ctrl + Arrows</code> works as <code>Shift + Arrows</code>, but will not change the selection of files outside the current focus region.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        To select all files press <code>Ctrl + A</code>, or to unselect all image press <code>Ctrl + Shift + A</code>. These operations are also available from the
        <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>
        menu as
        <emphasis role="bold">Select all</emphasis>
        and
        <emphasis role="bold">Select none</emphasis>
        .
      </para>
      <para>
        The current number of selected images and their total size will be indicated in the File list section of the
        <link linkend="GuideMainWindowStatusBar">status bar</link>
        .
      </para>
      <para />
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Sorting">
    <title>Sorting</title>
    <para>The order of the images can be changed by clicking the sort area of the status bar or from the context menu. The sort methods are by file name, number, file date, or file size. The number method will sort file names by their natural order, for example files with names of file_10, file_12, and file_9 will appear in order file_9, file_10, and file_12.</para>
    <para>Selecting the ascending menu item will toggle between increasing and decreasing sort order.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Contextmenu">
    <title>Context menu</title>
    <para>
      Right clicking the mouse or pressing the menu key while the file pane has focus will display a menu. The menu functions will perform the same as those that match the window's
      <link linkend="GuideMainWindowMenus">menu bar</link>
      , however a few functions are unique to the context menu:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">View in new window</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Opens a new window containing a list of the currently selected images.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">Sort</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Changes the sort order of file pane.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">View as icons</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggles between the list and icon view modes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">Show thumbnails</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggles display of thumbnails in the list view display mode.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">Show filename text</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggles display of file names in the icon view display mode.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis role="bold">Show star rating</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggles display of the "star rating" (Xmp.xmp.Rating).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="DragandDrop">
    <title>Drag and Drop</title>
    <para>Drag and drop can be initialized with the primary or middle mouse buttons in the file pane. Dragging a file that is selected will include all selected files in the drag. Dragging a file that is not selected will first change the selection to the dragged file, and clear the previous selection.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
</section>
