<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideCollections">
  <title id="titleGuideCollections">Collections</title>
  <para>Geeqie provides the ability to build lists of images, regardless of the location of the files on disk.</para>
  <para>A collection window displays the contents of a collection. It allows the collection to be modified and access to the images contained in the collection.</para>
  <para>
    To open a new empty collection window select
    <menuchoice>
      <shortcut>
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>C</keycap>
        </keycombo>
      </shortcut>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>New collection</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    .
  </para>
  <para>
    To open an existing collection, select
    <menuchoice>
      <shortcut>
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>O</keycap>
        </keycombo>
      </shortcut>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Open collection</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    . A dialog will appear requesting the location of the collection file. A window will the open containing the selected collection. Recently opened or saved collections can also be opened by selecting the collection's file name from the Open recent sub menu of the file menu.
  </para>
  <para>
    To delete or rename a collection, select
    <menuchoice>
      <shortcut>
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>O</keycap>
        </keycombo>
      </shortcut>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Open collection</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    , right-click on the collection you wish to delete or rename, and then select
    <emphasis role="strong">Delete</emphasis>
    or
    <emphasis role="strong">Rename</emphasis>
    .
  </para>
  <para>The collection window consists of a pane to display the contents of the collection, and a status bar along the bottom of the window.</para>
  <para />
  <section id="Iconpane">
    <title>Icon pane</title>
    <para>The icon pane displays images contained in the collection as thumbnails in a grid, by default the file names also appear below each thumbnail.</para>
    <para>
      The Icon pane works exactly like the Icon view mode of the
      <link linkend="GuideMainWindowFilePane" endterm="titleGuideMainWindowFilePane" />
      in a main window, but with the addition that the contents of the collection can be organized with drag and drop.
    </para>
    <para>
      A
      <emphasis role="strong">context menu</emphasis>
      is available for the icon pane by right clicking the mouse or pressing the Menu key.
    </para>
    <para>
      <link linkend="GuideReferenceKeyboardShortcuts" endterm="titleGuideReferenceKeyboardShortcuts" />
      are available in the collection window:
    </para>
    <para>
      The
      <emphasis role="strong">selection</emphasis>
      can be changed using the keyboard and mouse the same as in a
      <link linkend="GuideMainWindowFilePane" endterm="titleGuideMainWindowFilePane" />
      of the main window.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Statusbar">
    <title>Status bar</title>
    <para>The status bar displays the total number of images in the collection, and the number of selected images in parenthesis. A progress bar also displays whenever thumbnails are loading from disk.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="DragandDrop">
    <title>Drag and Drop</title>
    <para>Drag and drop can be initialized with the primary or middle mouse buttons. Dragging an image that is selected will include all selected images in the drag. Dragging an image that is not selected will drag only that image.</para>
    <para>Dropping files and folders onto the collection window will add them to the collection, they will be inserted at the location of the drop. A red arrow will indicate the location of the drop as files are dragged over the collection window. When one or more folders are included in the drop list, a menu will appear to select how to handle the contents of the folders.</para>
    <para>To move images within the collection to change their order, initiate a drag for the selected image(s) and then move the mouse to the desired location within the window. A red arrow will appear to assist in determining the destination of the dragged images. Release the drag to move the images to the new location in the list.</para>
    <note>
      <para>
        When renaming or moving files within Geeqie, the contents of collections located in the
        <link linkend="GuideReferenceConfig">collections folder</link>
        will automatically update to the new name or location.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="AppendImages">
    <title>Append Images</title>
    <para>Right-click menu items permit images to be appended from either another collection or from the currently selected folder.</para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="RandomizedSort">
    <title>Randomized Sort</title>
    <para>
      Right-click menu item
      <emphasis role="strong">Sort</emphasis>
      , in addition to the standard sort methods, permits images to be randomly arranged.
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
</section>
