<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideOptionsFiltering">
  <title id="titleGuideOptionsFiltering">Files Options</title>
  <para>This section describes the options presented under the Files Tab of the preferences dialogue.</para>
  <para />
  <section id="Filters">
    <title>Filters</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Show hidden files or folders</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enables the display of hidden files and folders, also known as dot files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Show parent folder</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enables the display of the parent folder as a double dot in the directories views.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Case sensitive sort</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Files and folders are sorted such that upper case letters occur before lower case letters.</para>
          <para>
            Enabled result: A, B, C, a, b, c
            <para />
            Disabled result: A, a, B, b, C, c
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Natural sort order</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Files and folders are sorted with the dot '.' treated as a special case, so the order is e.g. "event.c" "event.h" "eventgenerator.c". Also, files containing numbers are sorted as "file1" "file5" "file10".</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Disable file extension checks</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>During rename operations, allows files to be renamed to a different extension with no warning issued.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Disable file filtering</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable this to allow Geeqie to list all files, even those that do not contain images.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Groupingsidecarextensions">
    <title>Grouping sidecar extensions</title>
    <para>This field defines which extensions will lead to file grouping. Grouped files will appear as a single entry in file views. This is useful, for example, when browsing directories containing two files for the same image (such as raw+jpeg files generated by some cameras).</para>
    <para>The group is represented by the first extension in the list for which a file exists.</para>
    <para>
      Each extension should include the starting dot and should be separated by a semi-colon from following entries. It is possible to use wild-cards corresponding to entries in the
      <emphasis>File Types Class</emphasis>
      below:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>%unknown</literal>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            expands to all files listed in class
            <emphasis>Unknown</emphasis>
            ,
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>%image</literal>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            expands to all files listed in class
            <emphasis>Image</emphasis>
            ,
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>%raw</literal>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            expands to all files listed in class
            <emphasis>RAW Image</emphasis>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>%meta</literal>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            expands to all files listed in class
            <emphasis>Metadata</emphasis>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para />
    <para />
  </section>
  <section id="Filetypes">
    <title>File types</title>
    <para>
      This list contains the image formats that are understood by Geeqie. To disable a specific file type from being displayed, uncheck it's corresponding check-box. Filters can be edited by first selecting the line containing the item to be changed, then clicking the filter or description field, making any changes, then pressing
      <keycap>Enter</keycap>
      ; press
      <keycap>Escape</keycap>
      to cancel an active edit.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>Unlike all other options in the dialogue, filter list changes are applied immediately.</para>
    </note>
    <para>
      The table consists of:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Filter</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            List of extensions this filter applies to, separated by a
            <code>;</code>
            . Each extension must be preceded by a dot.
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Description</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>Brief description. This is not used elsewhere.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Class</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            This may be used to define sets of file types, for use in the
            <emphasis>Grouping</emphasis>
            function described above. The drop-down list has 7 entries:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>Unknown</listitem>
              <listitem>Image</listitem>
              <listitem>RAW Image</listitem>
              <listitem>Metadata</listitem>
              <listitem>Video</listitem>
              <listitem>Collection</listitem>
              <listitem>Document</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Writable</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>If this option is checked, Geeqie will try to write metadata to the image file itself. This, and the following option, are mutually exclusive.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Sidecar is allowed</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>If this option is checked, Geeqie will try to write metadata to a sidecar file associated with the image. This, and the previous option, are mutually exclusive.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guibutton>
            <guiicon>
              <inlinegraphic fileref="list-add.png" />
            </guiicon>
            Add
          </guibutton>
        </term>
        <listitem>Adds a new blank line to the filter list, change the parameters to match the desired file type.</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guibutton>
            <guiicon>
              <inlinegraphic fileref="list-remove.png" />
            </guiicon>
            Remove
          </guibutton>
        </term>
        <listitem>Removes the selected line from the filter list.</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guibutton>Defaults</guibutton>
        </term>
        <listitem>Resets the filter list to the default values, discarding any customizations made by the user.</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</section>
