<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="GuideImageSearch">
  <title id="titleGuideImageSearch">Search and Select</title>
  <para>Geeqie provides comprehensive set of search methods, including not only the standard functions such as file date or size, but also image similarity.</para>
  <para>There is a duplicate file finder, which uses search parameters such as image dimensions or checksum. Two sets of image files may be compared.</para>
  <para>Geeqie also has a set of temporary "marks" or "tags" which may be allocated to any image as an aide to file organising.</para>
  <section id="GuideImageSearchCache">
    <title id="titleGuideImageSearchCache">Caching Data For Searches</title>
    <para>
      Searching large numbers of files for similarity can take significant cpu time. Part of this is the time to compute the similarity matrix for each file.
      <para />
      If the
      <link linkend="PreferencesThumbnails">Cache Thumbnails</link>
      option is selected in Preferences/General, the similarity matrix and the checksum will also be cached. This will reduce the time needed for future searches.
      <note>If you frequently search on similarity and your images are in a tree arrangement under a single point, initiating a one-time search on similarity from the top of the tree will generate the similarity data for all images.</note>
      <para>Similarity data are stored in a folder hierachy that mirrors the location of the source images. The data have the same name as the original appended by the file extension .sim.</para>
      <para>
        The root of the hierachy is:
        <para>
          <programlisting>$XDG_CACHE_HOME/geeqie/thumbnails/</programlisting>
          or, if $XDG_CACHE_HOME is not defined:
          <programlisting>$HOME/.cache/geeqie/thumbnails/</programlisting>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para />
  </section>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="GuideImageSearchSearch.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="GuideImageSearchFindingDuplicates.xml" />
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="GuideImageMarks.xml" />
  <para />
</chapter>
